Guide to the Ambassador Auditorium Collection ARS.0043
Archive of Recorded Sound
Ambassador Auditorium Collection
1974-1995
Archive of Recorded Sound
ARS.0043
636 box(es) Containers of various sizes with multiple types of print materials, photographic materials, audio and video materials, realia, posters and original art work (682.05 linear ft.).
The Ambassador Auditorium Collection contains the files of the various organizational departments of the Ambassador Auditorium as well as audio and video recordings. The materials cover the entire time period of April 1974 through May 1995 when the Ambassador Auditorium was fully operational as an internationally recognized concert venue. The materials in this collection cover all aspects of concert production and presentation, including documentation of the concert artists and repertoire as well as many business documents, advertising, promotion and marketing files, correspondence, inter-office memos and negotiations with booking agents. The materials are widely varied and include concert program booklets, audio and video recordings, concert season planning materials, artist publicity materials, individual event files, posters, photographs, scrapbooks and original artwork used for publicity. Many of the print materials include handwritten comments from office personnel and administrators, and many of the artist photographs are autographed. Since the various office personnel maintained their own files, and the same information was often needed in more than one office at a time, the collection contains duplicate copies of many items. Although efforts were made to eliminate duplicate material from the same file or the same series, duplicate copies of items exist among the files from different offices. In an effort to maintain the original content of these files, the cross-file duplicate items were retained in the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in ten series according to the original order established by the Ambassador Auditorium personnel: (1) Administrative Files; (2) Concert Files; (3) Concert Management and Booking Files; (4) Concert Program Files; (5) Publicity and Advertising; (6) Marketing Files; (7) Broadcast Media Associate Files and Media Relations/In Recital Files; (8) Performance Files; (9) Miscellaneous Materials: Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous Signed Photographs, Artwork Assigned to Scrapbooks; (10) Concert Recordings. Sub-Series have been established for audio and video recordings.
In general, the original order of materials has been maintained to provide a contextual relationship of individual items within each series and within the total collection. Although many of the files were originally organized either alphabetically or chronologically, there seem to be inconsistencies in the filing systems used by the Ambassador personnel. Filing procedures within a single office appeared to have changed over time, or in some cases it appears that different filing systems were used simultaneously. To a large degree, these variants in filing procedure have been maintained with occasional small adjustments made to group together certain related materials when it made sense to do so.
Biographical / Historical
The Ambassador Auditorium is located on the grounds of Maranatha High School (formerly the campus of Ambassador College) in Pasadena, California. The Ambassador was built under the guidance of Herbert W. Armstrong as a facility for religious services of the Worldwide Church of God and also as a performing arts center. The architectural design of the building bears certain similarities to that of the Temple of ancient Israel.
The first public concert at the Ambassador was presented by the Vienna Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Carlo Maria Giulini, on April 7, 1974. For the next twenty years the Ambassador hosted many of the world’s finest performing artists in many genres, and thus it was known as “The Carnegie Hall of the West.” Notable artists who performed at the Ambassador included Artur Rubinstein, Leontyne Price, Victor Borge, Peter Schickele as P.D.Q. Bach, Julian Bream, Andrés Segovia, Barbara Cook, Juilliard String Quartet, Los Angeles Chamber Orchestra, Yo-Yo Ma, Philharmonia Baroque Orchestra, Jean-Pierre Rampal, Bing Crosby, Bob Hope, the Chieftains, the Kingston Trio, Emmylou Harris, Alison Krauss, Marcel Marceau, Claire Bloom, Count Basie, Benny Goodman, Modern Jazz Quartet, Oscar Peterson, Ravi Shankar, Mel Tormé, and the Dance Theatre of Harlem. During this period the Ambassador also hosted the inaugural Ivo Pogorelich International Solo Piano Competition as well as the Pasadena Jazz Festival. The interior design of the hall was noted for its exceptional elegance displaying Iranian onyx, African teak wood, gold overlay and wool carpets from India. Due to the relatively small seating capacity of the main hall with 1262 seats (compared with Carnegie Hall’s Isaac Stern Auditorium which has 2804 seats), the Ambassador was particularly well suited to small ensembles and solo performances. In the mid 1990s the Worldwide Church of God, which operated the Ambassador Auditorium and Ambassador College, ceased its operations and sold the property. In 2004 a portion of the property, including the Ambassador Auditorium, was purchased by HRock Church of Pasadena.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Listening appointments may require 24 hours notice. Contact the Archive Operations Manager.
Scope and Contents
The Ambassador Auditorium Collection was assembled and donated by the Ambassador Foundation in 2001. The collection consists of over 600 boxes of concert information and documentation from the numerous files of the Ambassador Auditorium during the period of April 1974 through May 1995. The materials include concert program booklets, concert and promotional audio and video recordings, concert season planning materials, artist publicity materials, individual event files, posters, photographs, scrapbooks, original artwork used for publicity, and so far is as known, the complete office files from the various departments of the Ambassador Auditorium including some correspondence and inter-office memos.
Music publicity; Concert programs; Advertising departments; Centers for the performing arts -- California; Entertainers -- Photographs; Advertising fliers; Musicians -- Photographs; Auditoriums -- California; Worldwide Church of God; American Federation of Musicians; Pasadena Jazz Festival; Ivo Pogorelich International Solo Piano Competition; Ambassador Hall (Pasadena, Calif.); Ambassador International Cultural Foundation; Armstrong, Herbert W.
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 59 boxes + 1 folder (64.4 linear feet)
  General
  The Administrative Files contain a mixture of paper and photographic materials and a variety of audio and video recordings. Some recordings document performances that took place at the Ambassador Auditorium, and for those recordings program information has been provided when it was available.
  - Audio Recordings: Radio Promotional Spots:, 1981 -- 1995; 77 audio cassettes; 34 5" open reel tapes; 5 7" open reel tapes (Box 599)
    Scope and Contents
    Audio cassette and open reel tapes containing radio promotional spots for numerous artists who appeared at the Ambassador. Some tapes are labeled for broadcast on specific Southern California radio stations, including KABC, KAJZ/KBJZ, K-BIG, KCRW, KCSN, KFAC, K-FROG, KFWB, KGIL, KIK, KKGO, KLSX, KNX, KSKQ, KTWV, KUSC, KXEZ, and KZLA. The majority of the tapes contain the name of the performance being advertised, and some tapes are also labeled with date information and/or the length of the radio spot(s).
    NB: One audio cassette tape containing a radio promotional spot for Mr. Jack Daniel's Original Silver Cornet Band was removed from Series 5, Box 180, Folder 6.180.9 and relocated in this box.
  - Audio Recordings: Radio Promotional Spots:, 1981 -- 1995; 200 audio cassettes (Box 600)
    Audio cassette tapes containing radio promotional spots for numerous artists who appeared at the Ambassador. Some tapes are labeled for broadcast on specific Southern California radio stations, including KABC, KAJZ/KBJZ, K-BIG, KCRW, KCSN, KFAC, K-FROG, KFWB, KGIL, KIK, KKGO, KLSX, KNX, KSKQ, KTWV, KUSC, KXEZ, and KZLA. The majority of the tapes contain the name of the performance being advertised, and some tapes are also labeled with date information and/or the length of the radio spot(s).
  - Audio Recordings: Radio Promotional Spots:, 1981 -- 1995; 102 audio cassettes (Box 601)
    Arrangement
    These audio recordings are boxed together with audio cassette tapes of Ambassador performances (the two groups of materials have been clearly separated within the box). For a description of the performance tapes, see Box 601 in Series 10.
  - Audio Recordings: Radio Promotional Spots:, 1988 -- 1991; 32 7" open reel tapes; 3 10 1/2" open reel tapes (Box 406)
    The bulk of these 35 open reel tapes contain radio promotional spots for performances at the Ambassador. The tapes have been left in original order due to the limited amount of information available.
  - Audio Recordings: Demo/Promotional and Radio Interviews and Performances:, 1976 -- 1995; 153 audio cassettes; 5 7" open reel tapes; 3 DATs (Box 602)
    The recordings in this box are divided into two categories. Placed on top within the box are 3 DATs (digital audio tapes) and 43 audio cassettes. These recordings consist of radio programs and interviews broadcast on various stations, including KCRW, KFAC, KGIL, KJOI, KKGO, KLON, KPCC, KPFK, KUSC, WBGO, and WQXR. Interviewers and radio personalities represented include Jerry Bishop (KGIL), Gail Eichenthal, Bonnie Grice (KUSC), Greg Hettmansberger (NPR’s “Performance Today”), Isabel Holt, Fred Hyatt, Branford Marsalis (JazzSet), Duff Murphy (KPCC), Chuck Niles, John Santana (KKGO’s “In the Wings”), Tom Schnabel (KCRW), John Schneider (KPFK), Judith Schonbach (NPR’s “Morning Edition”), Chuck Southcott (KJOI), and Jim Svedja (KUSC). Artists featured and/or interviewed include Donald Adams, Cecilia Bartoli, Valentin Berlinsky (Borodin Quartet), Teresa Brewer, Chick Corea, Gary Crosby, Anne-Sophie Mutter (Mutter did not perform at the Ambassador, though she was included in the proposed 1995-1996 concert season, which did not take place), Pasadena Jazz Festival performers (Dori Caymmi, Clayton-Hamilton Jazz Orchestra, Benny Green, Ken Peplowski, Frank Vignola, and Rickey Woodard), the Pied Pipers, Ivo Pogorelich, Pogorelich Competition contestants (Edith Chen, Michael Kieran Harvey, Irina Plotnikova, Evgeny Zarafiants), Pepe Romero, Richard Sheldon, and Billy Taylor.
    The other 110 cassettes and 5 7" open reel tapes in the box are miscellaneous demo or promotional recordings by various artists, arranged roughly in alphabetical order according to performer name (This box contains the sequence A - D; D - N is located in Box 603 and N - Z in Box 604). Some of the artists represented in these recordings performed at the Ambassador, though the majority did not.
    NB: One promotional audio cassette tape (Bulgarian Women's Choir: Le Mystere Des Voix Bulgares, Vol. Two) was removed from Series 5, Box 141, Folder 5.141.1 and relocated in this box.
    Demo recordings; Pasadena Jazz Festival; Ivo Pogorelich International Solo Piano Competition
  - Audio Recordings: Demo/Promotional:, 1976 -- 1995; 184 audio cassettes; 2 DATs (Box 603)
    The 184 cassettes and 2 DATs (digital audio tapes) in this box are miscellaneous demo or promotional recordings by various artists, arranged roughly in alphabetical order according to performer name (This box contains the sequence D - N; A - D is located in Box 602 and N - Z in Box 604). Some of the artists represented in these recordings performed at the Ambassador, though the majority did not.
    NB: Five copies of a promotional audio cassette sampler (Heinichen/Dresden Concerti & Venetian Vespers) were removed from Series 7, Box 239, Folder 7.239.7 and relocated in this box.
    Demo recordings
  - Audio Recordings: Demo/Promotional:, 1976 -- 1995; 180 audio cassettes (Box 604)
    The 180 cassettes in this box are miscellaneous demo or promotional recordings by various artists, arranged roughly in alphabetical order according to performer name (This box contains the sequence N - Z; A - D is located in Box 602 and D - N in Box 603). Some of the artists represented in these recordings performed at the Ambassador, though the majority did not.
  - Audio Recordings: Performances:, 1974 -- 1981; 31 7” open reel tapes; 3 empty tape boxes; 1 folder (Box 385)
    The 31 tapes in this box are recordings of performances at the Ambassador arranged in chronological order. Tapes are identified by date and performer(s). This box also contains one folder and three tape boxes which did not contain tapes but did include information about the lacking tapes.
    [Folder:] (1) [lists of performance recordings made at the Ambassador between 1974 and 1981, separated into the categories of 2 track, 4 track, 8 track and 16 track]
    [NB: Some of the tape boxes lack spine labels, though in most cases the back of the box is labeled. Some detached spine labels were found loose inside the larger storage container, and these have been placed inside the corresponding tape box.]
    02-02-1978: Andre Watts, piano: [for program information, see Tape (7803:1), Box 575]
    02-04-1978: Karan Armstrong, soprano; Russell Stepan, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7804:1-2), Box 447]
    02-16-1978: Carlo Bergonzi, tenor; John Wustman, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7805:1-2), Box 448]
    03-02-1978: Guarneri String Quartet: [for program information, see Tapes (7807:1-2), Box 448]
    03-04-1978: Jean-Philippe Collard, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7808:1-2), Box 448]
    03-06-1978: [3 tapes: one labeled “entire performance” and two labeled “Khachaturian only”] Utah Symphony Orchestra; Maurice Abravanel, music director/conductor; Dora Kuhn, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7809:1-2), Box 575]
    03-11-1978: Carlos Montoya, flamenco guitar: [NB: Tape container is incorrectly labeled 03-10-1978; for program information, see Tape (7811:1), Box 448]
    [04-15-1978?]: Pierre Fournier, violoncello: [for program information for 04-15-1978 performance with Janet Guggenheim, piano, see Tapes (7813:1-2), Box 448]
    [04-18-1978?]: Vladimir Spivakov, violin: [for program information for 04-18-1978 performance with Boris Bechterev, piano, see Tapes (7814:1-2), Box 449]
    10-07-1978: Luciano Pavarotti, tenor; John Wustman, piano, 10-07-1978: [for program information, see Tapes (7816:1-2), Box 440]
    10-09-1978: World of Gilbert and Sullivan: [for program information, see Tapes (7817:1-2), Box 449]
    10-23-1978: José Carreras, tenor; Martin Katz, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7818:1-2), Box 449]
    10-26-1978: Andre Watts, piano; Bernard Kruysen, baritone; Charles Treger, violin: Celebration of Schubert: [for program information, see Tapes (7819:1-2), Box 440]
    10-28-1978: Andre Watts, piano; Charles Treger, violin: Celebration of Schubert: [for program information, see Tapes (7820:1-2), Box 440]
    11-13-1978: Vienna Choir Boys [NB: Empty container; tape is missing]
    11-16-1978: I Musici [NB: Empty container; tape is missing]
    11-22-1978: Gerhard Oppitz [NB: Empty container; tape is missing. Lazar Berman performed on this date in place of Oppitz.]
    12-14-1978: Marilyn Horne, mezzo-soprano; Jacqueline Silver, piano; Myra Kestenbaum, viola: [for program information, see Tapes (7826:1-2), Box 451]
    12-16-1978: Daniel Pollack, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7827:1-2), Box 451]
    02-08-1979: Carmen Balthrop, soprano; Gregory Watson, piano; David Williams, bass: [for program information, see Tapes (7904:1-2), Box 452]
    02-12-1979: Delmoni Thomson Thomas String Trio: [for program information, see Tapes (7906:1-2), Box 452]
    02-13-1979: Clamma Dale, soprano; Neal Stannard, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7907:1-2), Box 452]
    03-20-1979: Daniel Adni, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7908:1-2), Box 442]
    03-22-1979: Henryk Szeryng, violin; Charles Reiner, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7909:1-2), Box 442]
    03-25-1979: Lazar Berman, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7910:1-2), Box 442]
    04-28-1979: New England Ragtime Ensemble: [NB: Tape container is incorrectly labeled 04-29-1979; no program listed]
    05-01-1979: Daniel Phillips, violin; Charles Abramovic, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7913:1-2), Box 443]
    05-05-1979: [2 tapes] Renata Scotto, soprano; John Atkins, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7914:1-2), Box 443]
    09-27-1979: Luciano Pavarotti, tenor; Los Angeles Chamber Orchestra (L.A.C.O.); Bruno Bartoletti, conductor: Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868. Cenerentola. Sinfonia -- Puccini, Giacomo, 1858-1924. Tosca. Recondita armonia -- Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901. Macbeth. Ah, la paterna mano -- Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901. Macbeth. [Title from program:] Dances -- Boito, Arrigo, 1842-1918. Mefistofele. Giunto sul passo estremo -- Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901. Luisa Miller. Quando le sere al placido -- Puccini, Giacomo, 1858-1924. Manon Lescaut. Intermezzo -- Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912. Werther. Pourquoi me réveiller -- Cilèa, Francesco, 1866-1950. Arlesiana. È la solita storia -- Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901. Vêpres siciliennes. Sinfonia -- Ponchielli, Amilcare, 1834-1886. Gioconda. Cielo e mar
    10-16-1979: Carlos Montoya, guitar: [for program information, see Tapes (7916:1-2), Box 443]
  - Audio Recordings: Performances:, 1979 -- 1980; 31 7” open reel tapes; 1 empty tape box (Box 386)
    The 31 tapes in this box are recordings of performances at the Ambassador arranged in chronological order. Tapes are identified by date and performer(s). This box also contains one tape box with tape lacking.
    11-05-1979: Andre Watts, piano, 11-05-1979: [for program information, see Tape (7919:2), Box 454]
    11-11-1979: Birgit Nilsson, soprano; John Wustman, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7920:1-2), Box 454]
    11-29-1979: Lazar Berman, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (7921:1-2), Box 455]
    01-29-1980: Panayis Lyras, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8002:1-2), Box 455]
    01-31-1980: Borodin Piano Trio: [for program information, see Tapes (8003:1-2), Box 455]
    02-03-1980: “The Pirates of Penzance” [Opera A La Carte]: Sullivan, Arthur, 1842-1900. Pirates of Penzance
    02-07-1980: Paul Rutman, piano: [for program information, see Tape (8004:2), Box 456]
    02-12-1980: Zehava Gal, mezzo-soprano; Lawrence Skrobacs, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8005:1-2), Box 456]
    02-20-1980: Yo-Yo Ma, cello; Emanuel Ax, piano: [for program information, see Tape (8007:2), Box 456]
    02-23-1980: Eliot Fisk, guitar: [for program information, see Tapes (8008:1-2), Box 456]
    02-24-1980: Charles Treger, violin; Andre Watts, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8009:1-2), Box 456]
    02-26-1980: Ida Kavafian, violin; Anne Epperson, piano: [for program information, see Tape (8010:2), Box 457]
    03-11-1980: Sergei Edelmann, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8011:1-2), Box 457]
    03-12-1980: Carlos Montoya, guitar: [for program information, see Tapes (8012:1-2), Box 457]
    03-15-1980: Michel Béroff, Jean-Philippe Collard, pianos: [for program information, see Tapes (8013:1-2), Box 457]
    03-20-1980: Virgil Fox, organ: [for program information, see Tapes (8014:1-3), Box 594]
    03-23-1980: [2 tapes] Boris Bloch, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8015:1-2), Box 457]
    03-24-1980: Diana Soviero, soprano; Judith Somogi, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8016:1-2), Box 457]
    04-03-1980: [2 tapes; one is dated “March 1980”] Youri Egorov, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8017:1-2), Box 458]
    04-15-1980: Ronald Thomas, cello; Stephen Swedish, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8019:1-2), Box 458]
    04-19-1980: Eighth Annual Opera Awards Auditions Finals (Zachary Contest): [for program information, see Tapes (8020:1-2), Box 458]
    04-22-1980: Alicia de Larrocha, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8021:1-2), Box 458]
    05-06-1980: Marya Martin, flute; Anne Epperson, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8003:1-2), Box 512]
    05-07-1980: Pasadena Youth Symphony [NB: Empty container; tape is missing]
    05-17-1980: Leonard Pennario, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8004:1-2), Box 512]
    10-07-1980: Tokyo String Quartet: [for program information, see Tapes (8005:1-2), Box 512]
    10-16-1980: Magda Tagliaferro, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8006:1-2), Box 512]
    10-19-1980: New England Ragtime Ensemble; Gunther Schuller, conductor: [no program listed]
    10-27-1980: Beaux Arts Trio: [for program information, see Tapes (8010:1-2), Box 512]
    [undated, ca. 1980?]: Jakob Gimpel, piano: [no program information available]
  - Audio Recordings: Performances:, 1980 -- 1981; 31 7” open reel tapes (Box 387)
    The 31 tapes in this box are recordings of performances at the Ambassador arranged in chronological order. Tapes are identified by date and performer(s).
    10-29-1980: [3 tapes] Gregory Allen, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8011:1-2), Box 513]
    11-15-1980: Peter Orth, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8012:1-2), Box 513]
    11-16-1980: A Classical/Jazz Celebration: Angel Romero, guitar; George Shearing, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8013:1-3), Box 513]
    11-18-1980: Narciso Yepes, guitar: [for program information, see Tapes (8014:1-2), Box 513]
    11-19-1980: Victoria de los Angeles, soprano; Eliot Fisk, guitar; David Shostac, flute: [for program information, see Tapes (8015:1-2), Box 513]
    11-20-1980: Les Menestrels, Viennese Ensemble for Early Music: [for program information, see Tapes (8016:1-2), Box 513]
    11-29-1980: Alfredo Kraus, tenor; Edelmiro Arnaltes, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8018:1-2), Box 513]
    12-02-1980: Philip Lorenz and Ena Bronstein, pianos: [for program information, see Tapes (8019:1-2), Box 514]
    12-10-1980: Benny Goodman Classical Trio (Benny Goodman, clarinet; Leslie Howard, piano; Nathaniel Rosen, cello): [for program information, see Tapes (8020:1-2), Box 514]
    12-11-1980: John Biggs Consort; John Biggs; Salli Terri: [for program information, see Tapes (8021:1-2), Box 514]
    01-10-1981: Pepe Romero, guitar: [for program information, see Tapes (8101:1-2), Box 514]
    01-15-1981: Bella Davidovich, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8102:1-2), Box 514]
    01-27-1981: Cleveland Quartet; Paula Robison, flute: [for program information, see Tapes (8105:1-2), Box 514]
    01-31-1981: Opera A La Carte, “Trial By Jury” and “Cox and Box”: [for program information, see Tapes (8107:1-2), Box 515]
    02-01-1981: Opera A La Carte, “Trial By Jury” and “Cox and Box”: [for program information, see Tapes (8108:1-2), Box 515]
    02-04-1981: Liona Boyd, guitar; Carol Wincenc, flute: [for program information, see Tapes (8110:1-2), Box 515]
    02-09-1981: [3 tapes] Sung-Ju Lee, violin; Richard Bishop, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8111:1-2), Box 515]
    02-10-1981: Claudio Arrau, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8112:1-2), Box 515]
    02-19-1981: Consortium Antiquum [Renaissance dancers Angene Feves and Charles Perrier]: [for program information, see Tapes (8113:1-2), Box 515]
    02-23-1981: Colin Carr, cello; Kathryn Stott, piano: [for program information, see Tapes (8114:1-2), Box 515]
    02-24-1981: New Arts Trio: [for program information, see Tapes (8115:1-2), Box 516]